Tilton Textile Corporation Photographs 6918 P
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Tilton Textile Corporation Photographs
1939-1945
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Tilton Textile Corporation
American Textile History Museum
6918 P
1 folders
Interior views of the Lone Star Cotton Mills and its predecessor, the El Paso Cotton Mills, in El Paso, Texas.
1 file folder
Gelatin silver print, photographs.
10066170
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Biographical / Historical
The Tilton Textile Corporation, located in New York City, acted as selling agents and textile converters. It owned most of the stock in and acted as selling agent for the Lone Star Cotton Mills Company, El Paso, Texas. Lone Star incorporated in 1924 under the name El Paso Cotton Mills Company; in 1940 it amended its charter and changed its name to Lone Star Cotton Mills. The company ceased production around 1980.
Custodial History
American Textile History Museum Collection, gift of Tilton Textile Corp.
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183 kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel-center
Compiled by:
R. Miles, October 16, 2017
EAD encoding:
Randall Miles, December 11, 2017
Related Materials
Related Collections: 6907 P: Ted Stone Collection of Lone Star Cotton Mills Photographs; 6918: Tilton Textile Corporation Records
Scope and Contents
Includes photographs of the opening room, drawing room, warping room, cloth room, boiler room, and machine shop in the El Paso Cotton Mills in the 1930s. Also includes photographs of spinning room, drawing frame, and a loom in the Lone Star Cotton Mills, circa 1945.
Cotton manufacture; Women employees; Male employees; Machine shops; Spinning machinery; Steam-boilers; Textile factories; Textile machinery; Textile workers; Weaving; El Paso (Tex.); Gerlach, J. G.; El Paso Cotton Mills Company (El Paso, Tex.); El Paso Photo Company; Heire Safety Boiler Company; Lone Star Cotton Mills, Inc.; Saco-Lowell Shops; American Textile History Museum
10066170
- Window display for Lone Star Cotton Mills, El Paso, Texas, ATHM# 0000.2120.1, 1939; black and white photograph; 25 x 20.25 cm. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Scope and Contents
  El Paso Photo Co., J.G. Gerlach, 504 N. Stanton St., Main 856, photographer. Gelatin silver print. Image depicts a window display highlighting the Lone Star Cotton Mills. Cotton duct and cotton drill are hung on either side of a center display of raw cotton, along with photos of different kinds of processes (lapping, carding, spinning, slubbing, winding, warping, looms, slashing), several slivers and thread on cones.
- Male employees in spinning room, Lone Star Cotton Mills, El Paso, Texas, ATHM# 0000.2120.3.1, 1945; black and white photograph; 25 x 20.25 cm. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Press Photo, J.G. Gerlach, El Paso Photo Co. Gelatin silver print. Image depicts the interior of the spinning room of the Lone Star Cotton Mills in El Paso, Texas. Two male workers tend to the machinery. Copy B.
- Male employees in spinning room, Lone Star Cotton Mills, El Paso, Texas, ATHM# 0000.2120.3.2, 1945; black and white photograph; 25 x 20.25 cm. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Press Photo, J.G. Gerlach, El Paso Photo Co. Gelatin silver print. Image depicts the interior of the spinning room of the Lone Star Cotton Mills in El Paso, Texas. Two male workers tend to the machinery. Copy A.
- Female employee at drawing frame, Lone Star Cotton Mills, Inc., El Paso Texas, ATHM# 0000.2120.4, 1945; black and white photograph; 20.25 x 25.25 cm. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Press Photo, J.G. Gerlach, El Paso Photo Co. Gelatin silver print. Image depicts a female employee working at a drawing frame (manufactured by the Saco-Lowell Shops) in the Lone Star Cotton Mills, Inc. in El Paso, Texas. A carding machine is in the right background; a male employee brings an empty can forward. Copy A.
- Teenaged male employee standing beside loom, Lone Star Cotton Mills, El Paso, Texas, ATHM# 0000.2120.5.1, 1945; black and white photograph; 25.25 x 20.25 cm. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Press Photo, J.G. Gerlach, El Paso Photo Co. Gelatin silver print. Image depicts a teenaged male employee holding a bolt of fabric next to a loom in the Lone Star Cotton Mills in El Paso, Texas. Another bolt of fabric stands on the floor behind him. The loom is extremely dirty with a large amount of cotton waste on it. Copy A.
- Teenaged male employee standing beside loom, Lone Star Cotton Mills, El Paso, Texas, ATHM# 0000.2120.5.2, 1945; black and white photograph; 24.75 x 20.25 cm. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Press Photo, J.G. Gerlach, El Paso Photo Co. Gelatin silver print. Image depicts a teenaged male employee holding a bolt of fabric next to a loom in the Lone Star Cotton Mills in El Paso, Texas. Another bolt of fabric stands on the floor behind him. The loom is extremely dirty with a large amount of cotton waste on it. Copy B.
- Opener room, El Paso Cotton Mills, El Paso, Texas, ATHM# 0000.2120.6, 1930s; black and white photograph; 25.5 x 19.5 cm. (w/out backing); 28 x 19.5 cm. (w/backing) (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Gelatin silver print. Image depicts the opener room in the El Paso Cotton Mills (El Paso Cotton Mills Company) in El Paso, Texas. The opening machinery on the left was manufactured by the Saco-Lowell Shops. Large bags of cotton on the floor and leaning against the wall on the right.
- Drawing room, El Paso Cotton Mills, El Paso, Texas, ATHM# 0000.2120.7, 1930s; black and white photograph; 25.25 x 19.5 cm. (w/out backing); 27.5 x 19.5 cm. (w/backing) (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Gelatin silver print. Image depicts the drawing room in the El Paso Cotton Mills (El Paso Cotton Mills Company) in El Paso, Texas. The drawing machinery here was manufactured by the Saco-Lowell Shops in 1924. Carding machinery is just visible in the background on the left. See items 9 and 10 in this folder for another view of this room.
- Another view of the drawing room, El Paso Cotton Mills, El Paso, Texas, ATHM# 0000.2120.8.1, 1930s; black and white photograph; Copy A. 25.25 x 19.75 cm. (w/out backing); 27.75 x 19.75 cm. (w/backing) (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Gelatin silver print. Image depicts the drawing room in the El Paso Cotton Mills (El Paso Cotton Mills Company) in El Paso, Texas, but from another angle than that seen in item 8 in this folder. The drawing machinery here was manufactured by the Saco-Lowell Shops in 1924. Empty roving cans are in the foreground. Carding machinery is just barely visible in the background. A male employee is just visible in the left background working at a desk.
- Another view of the drawing room, El Paso Cotton Mills, El Paso, Texas, ATHM# 0000.2120.8.2, 1930s; black and white photograph; 25.5 x 20.25 cm. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Gelatin silver print. Image depicts the drawing room in the El Paso Cotton Mills (El Paso Cotton Mills Company) in El Paso, Texas, but from another angle than that seen in item 8 in this folder. The drawing machinery here was manufactured by the Saco-Lowell Shops in 1924. Empty roving cans are in the foreground. Carding machinery is just barely visible in the background. A male employee is just visible in the left background working at a desk. Copy B.
- Spinning room, El Paso Cotton Mills, El Paso, Texas, ATHM# 0000.2120.9, 1930s; black and white photograph; 25.25 x 19.5 cm. (w/out backing); 27.75 x 19.5 cm. (w/backing) (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Gelatin silver print. Image depicts the spinning room in the El Paso Cotton Mills (El Paso Cotton Mills Company) in El Paso, Texas. No employees visible.
- Spooling machinery, El Paso Cotton Mills, El Paso, Texas, ATHM# 0000.2120.10, 1930s; black and white photograph; 25.5 x 19.5 cm. (w/out backing); 27.5 x 19.5 cm. (w/backing) (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Gelatin silver print. Image depicts spooling machinery in the El Paso Cotton Mills (El Paso Cotton Mills Company) in El Paso, Texas. No employees visible.
- Warping room, El Paso Cotton Mills, El Paso, Texas, ATHM# 0000.2120.11, 1930s; black and white photograph; 25.5 x 19.5 cm. (w/out backing); 28 x 19.5 cm. (w/backing) (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Gelatin silver print. Image depicts the warping room in the El Paso Cotton Mills (El Paso Cotton Mills Company) in El Paso, Texas. The machine in the foreground is a beam warper; the two machines in the background are ball warpers. No employees visible.
- Slasher or sizing machinery, El Paso Cotton Mills, El Paso, Texas, ATHM# 0000.2120.12, 1930s; black and white photograph; 25.5 x 19.5 cm. (w/out backing); 27.75 x 19.5 cm. (w/backing) (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Gelatin silver print. Image depicts either slasher or sizing machinery in the El Paso Cotton Mills (El Paso Cotton Mills Company) in El Paso, Texas. A slasher is used for applying a size mixture to warp yarns. No employees visible.
- Unknown operation, El Paso Cotton Mills, El Paso, Texas, ATHM# 0000.2120.13, 1930s; black and white photograph; 25.5 x 19.5 cm. (w/out backing); 27.75 x 19.5 cm. (w/backing) (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Gelatin silver print. Image depicts a room in the El Paso Cotton Mills (El Paso Cotton Mills Company) in El Paso, Texas, but it is unclear what the machinery in the room is for. There are a number of reeds stacked against the wall and possibly extra spindles or bobbins in the open cabinet in the back, but the use of the machine in the center is unknown. The sign on the back wall, on the left, reads "Do Not Spit on the Floors Use Cuspidors."
- Cloth room, El Paso Cotton Mills, El Paso, Texas, ATHM# 0000.2120.14, 1930s; black and white photograph; 25.25 x 19.5 cm. (w/out backing); 27.75 x 19.5 cm. (w/backing) (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Gelatin silver print. Image depicts the cloth room in the El Paso Cotton Mills (El Paso Cotton Mills Company) in El Paso, Texas. Rolls of cloth stand on the floor in the foreground and against the wall on the side. Note the No Smoking sign in Spanish ("Se Prohibe Fumar") pasted on the interior windows. Folded cloth packages are visible on the table against the wall in the background.
- Boiler room, El Paso Cotton Mills, El Paso, Texas, ATHM# 0000.2120.15, 1930s; black and white photograph; 25.5 x 19.5 cm. (w/out backing); 27.75 x 19.5 cm. (w/backing) (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Gelatin silver print. Image depicts the boiler room in the El Paso Cotton Mills (El Paso Cotton Mills Company) in El Paso, Texas. Steam boilers built by the Heire Safety Boiler Company are shown. Note the No Smoking sign propped against the pipes: "No Smoking in or around mills a fire will throw us all out of a job."
- Machine shop, El Paso Cotton Mills, El Paso, Texas, ATHM# 0000.2120.16, 1930s; black and white photograph; 25.5 x 20.25 cm. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Gelatin silver print, 193-?. Image depicts the machine shop in the El Paso Cotton Mills (El Paso Cotton Mills Company) in El Paso, Texas. Both a lathe and a grinder are visible in the room, besides other equipment. The sign on the framework at the rear reads "Danger High Voltage" in both English and Spanish.